in this video i'm going to show you how
to solve some basic problems
dealing with organ pipes
pipes that are open at both ends and the
one that's closed or open at just one
end
so in this problem we have an organ pipe
that is 0.85 meters long
and it's open at both ends
what is the fundamental frequency at a
temperature of 15 degrees celsius
well the first thing we need to do is
calculate the velocity
we can approximate the velocity using
this equation it's 331 meters per second
plus
0.6 times t
where t is in celsius
so it's 331 plus 0.6
times 15 degrees celsius
so at this temperature
the speed of sound in air is 340 meters
per second
so now let's calculate the fundamental
frequency
to find it
it's nv
over 2l
for this type of pipe
so we're looking for the fundamental
frequency
so n is one
the speed is 340
and the length of the pipe
is 0.85 meters
so it's 340 divided by
let's see 2 times 0.85 that's 1.7
so the fundamental frequency in this
problem
is 200 hertz
so now that we have that we can
calculate
the frequency of the fourth harmonic
so that's f4
which is simply four times f1
so it's four times the fundamental
frequency
and four times 200
is 800 hertz
so that's the answer to part b
now part c
what is the frequency of the fifth
overtone
so how can we find that answer
now you need to know that the first
overtone i'm going to use ot for
overtone
represents the second harmonic or f2
the second overtone
corresponds to the third harmonic
and so the fifth overtone
corresponds to the six harmonic
so we're looking for the frequency of
the sixth harmonic
so that's going to be f6 which is
six times the fundamental frequency
or six times 200
which is 1200
so that's the frequency of the fifth
overtone
now let's move on to part d what is the
wavelength of the second overtone
the second overtone corresponds to the
third harmonic
and to calculate the wavelength
we could use this equation
it's 2l divided by m
so n in this example is 3 because we're
dealing with the second overtone or the
third harmonic
so this is going to be 2 times the
length of the pipe which is 0.85 meters
divided by n which is 3.
so 2 times 0.85 that's 1.7
divided by 3.
so the wavelength for the third harmonic
is
0.567
meters
now there's another way in which you can
get the same answer
now keep in mind that the speed is the
wavelength times the frequency
so if we want to find the wavelength of
the third harmonic it's going to be the
speed divided by the frequency of the
third harmonic
so the speed at 15 degrees celsius is
340 meters per second
and the frequency of the third harmonic
it's going to be three times the
fundamental frequency
or three times 200
which is 600 hertz
so we need to put that here
so 340 divided by 600
will give us the same answer of
0.567 meters
so now you have two ways in which you
can calculate the wavelength of a
certain harmonic
number two a closed organ pipe is 0.5
meters long
what is the fundamental frequency of
this pipe at 15 degrees celsius
so in a closed pipe
it's only closed at one end an open pipe
is open at both ends
so this closed pipe is 0.5 meters long
and the formula that we need to
calculate the fundamental frequency
is this equation it's nv divided by 4l
for an open pipe it was nv over 2l so
note the difference
now at 15 degrees celsius we know that
the speed
is going to be 340 meters per second
so the fundamental frequency occurs when
n is one so it's going to be 1 times 340
divided by 4 l where l is 0.5
so half of 4 is 2 so this is 340 divided
by
2 which is 170 hertz
so that's the fundamental frequency
in part a
now what about part b
what is the frequency of the third
overtone
now the third overtone is not the fourth
harmonic so the answer is not 170 times
four
it's not 680 hertz
now for the closed pipe
compared to the open pipe
the numbers are different
for the open pipe n could be 1 2 3 4 5
and so forth
for the closed pipe and can only be odd
numbers
so for the open pipe
the second
the first overtone
corresponds to n equals two or the
second harmonic
the second overtone
corresponds to the third harmonic
and the third overtone
corresponds to the fourth harmonic
the situation is different for a closed
pipe
the first overtone that's the first
frequency above the fundamental
frequency that's the third harmonic
the second overtone
is the fifth harmonic and the third
overtone
is the seventh harmonic
so in this case
n is 7 for part b we're looking for
the frequency of the seventh harmonic
the frequency of the seventh harmonic is
seven times the fundamental
so that's going to be seven
times 170
which is
1190 hertz
and so that's it for part b now part c
what is the wavelength of the second
overtone
we said the first circle tone
corresponds to n equals three n equals
five is the second overtone
so we need to find
the wavelength
of the fifth harmonic
where n is five
so the formula to calculate the
wavelength is this equation
it's equal to 4
l divided by
n
so l is 0.5 in this example
and n
is 5. we're dealing with the fifth
harmonic or the second overtone
so 4 times 0.5 divided by 5
will give us a wavelength
of 0.4 meters
now let's confirm it with the other
equation
so we know that v is equal to lambda
times frequency
so the fifth
the wavelength of the fifth harmonic is
the speed times the frequency of the
fifth harmonic
so let's calculate the frequency of the
fifth harmonic first
so that's going to be f5
which is 5 times 170
and so that's 850 hertz
so the wavelength is going to be the
speed at 15 degrees celsius which is
340 meters per second
times the frequency of 850 hertz
and that will give you the same answer
of 0.4 meters
so that's the wavelength
of the fifth harmonic or the second
overtone
so here's the last problem
an organ pipe can produce two successive
harmonics
at 750 hertz and 1050 hertz
what is the fundamental frequency
in order to find it we need to take the
difference of these two values because
it can help us to calculate the other
harmonics
so 1050 minus 750 is 300 hertz
so if you take 1050 and subtract it by
300 you get 750. if you take 750
subtracted by 300
you get the next harmonic that's 450.
and if you take 450 subtracted by 300
it's 150.
if you take 150 subtracted by 300 you're
going to get a negative number which
means this is the lowest frequency so
that has to be the fundamental
now this is how we can tell if it's an
open or closed
pipe if it's open
then n could be any number 1 two three
four and so forth if it's closed
and can only be odd numbers
one three five
well the second harmonic would be two
times one fifty which is three hundred
we don't have a value for 300
so this cannot be an open pipe so what
we have is a closed pipe
the third harmonic three times 150 that
will give us 450. the fifth harmonic
5 times 150 will give us 750 and the
seventh harmonic
which is seven times 150 will give us
1050.
so that's how we know for sure that we
have a closed pipe as opposed to an open
now let's move on to part c
what is the length of the pipe
so let's start with this equation
the frequency is nv over 4l
for a closed pipe
so let's cross multiply this is going to
be nv and that's equal to the frequency
times
4l
so l
is going to be nv divided by 4 times the
frequency
so let's use the fundamental frequency
where n is 1.
so v
let's use 340 meters per second i didn't
specify the temperature but
you can adjust the speed accordingly for
different problems
so we'll stick to the same speed that
we've been using
and the fundamental we see that it's 150
so it's going to be 340
divided by
4 times 150 which is basically 600.
and so the length of this pipe is 0.567
meters
and so that's it for this problem
you